[MUSIC]
[음악]
And so, let's actually compute TF/IDF.
TF-IDF를 실제로 계산해 보죠
Now, I can't just compute TF/IDF and this is an important note by the way.
이건 주의해야 할 점인데
Can't just compute TF/IDF for
오바마 문서의 TF-IDF만을 따로 떼서
the Obama article in isolation because tf/idf depends on entire corpus.
계산할 수 없는데 TF-IDF는 전체 말뭉치에 종속적이기 때문입니다
You need that normalizer which is the number of times a word appears in
모든 문서에서 등장하는 단어수를
every article.
정규화해야만 하죠
So, I have to show it I have computed for the entire corpus.
그러니 전체 말뭉치부터 계산해야 합니다
So let's go ahead and do just that.
한 번 해볼까요
So here we go, so
그럼
I'm gonna compute
말뭉치의
TF/IDF for the corpus.
TF-IDF를 계산합니다
And I'm gonna do this in two steps.
두 단계로 나누어서 진행합니다
First, I'm gonna compute the word counts for the entire corpus.
먼저 전체 말뭉치의 단어수를 계산합니다
So, I'm gonna add a new column to the people table called word_count.
인물 표에 word_count란 열을 추가합니다
Remember we just did this only for Barack Obama, so now, we're gonna do it for
현재는 바락 오바마에 대해서만 되어 있는데
everyone.
모든 사람을 대상으로 합니다
So I'm gonna call, graphlab.text_analytics.count_words and
graphlab.text_analytics.count_words을 호출하고
I'm going got put in the input,
입력으로 텍스트 열을
which is gonna be the the text column.
넣습니다
In other words, I'm gonna count the words in the text column.
즉 텍스트 열의 단어수를 셉니다
And just so that we're clear.
분명히 하자면 그렇죠
Then you just print the SFrame people after we do this,
그다음 SFrame people을 출력합니다
so I'm gonna print the first few lines of that SFrame.
SFrame의 처음 몇 줄을 출력합니다
So here we are, we've executed.
실행하면 이렇게 나오죠
Now we have the URI column, the location, the webpage, the name of person,
URI 열과, 위치, 웹페이지, 이름,
text, and now we have this dictionary of word counts on the right, the new column.
텍스트, 단어수 사전이 오른쪽에 추가되어있습니다
Good, so next we're gonna compute the TF/IDFs.
좋습니다. 이제 TF-IDF를 계산하죠
So just like with word counts, you can implement your own TF/IDF system,
단어수와 같이 TF-IDF 시스템을 직접 구현해야 되지만
it will take you a little while to do.
시간이 걸릴 것입니다
So, Graphlocate one already implemented, and
graphlab에 이미 구현되어 있으니
we're just gonna use that to make this whole process pretty quick,
시간을 단축하기 위해 구현된 걸 씁니다
so we're gonna call graphlab.text_analytics.
graphlab.text_analytics을 호출합니다
Just like with word count, there's a function here, .tf_idf.
단어수와 같이 tf_idf란 함수가 있습니다
And all you need to do is give an input,
입력만 넣으면 되는데
just like we're gonna give in the input the word_count.
word_count를 넣습니다
word_count, and it will output the TF/IDF.
그러면 TF-IDF가 출력됩니다
And let me just again show you what that looks like.
어떤 모습일지 보여드리죠
Oops, I did a little typo here.
아 오타가 있었네요
That should be word_count.
word_count가 되어야 합니다
That's call not word_counts.
word_counts가 아니라요
And now I'm going through the whole corpus,with 50,000 documents.
문서 50000개의 전체 말뭉치애서
Computing the frequency of words, normalizing.
단어 빈도를 계산, 정규화합니다
And what we end up with is a table where for every document, it calls the table
그러면 각 문서에 대한 표가 나오게 되는데
docs, it has a dictionary of TF/IDF's for each one of those documents.
각 문서의 TF-IDF 사전입니다
And just so that we get all this right, I'm gonna add a new column.
인물 표에 새로운 열 TF-IDF를
To the people table, and this new column is gonna be called tfidf,
추가합니다
and I'm just gonna store in there the tfidf's that I just computed.
방금 계산한 TF-IDF를 저장합니다
So it's all in one table, and it's a docs column.
표 하나에 전부 있고 그중 docs 열입니다
Here we go. We just added it in.
됐죠 방금 추가했습니다
So now we have tfidf's for every document computed and stored in there.
모든 문서에 대한 TF-IDF를 계산해서 넣었습니다
Let's do some examination.
검토하죠
So here's what we gonna do,
이제
we gonna Examine the TF-IDF for
오바마 문서의 TF-IDF를
the Obama article.
검토할 겁니다
So just like we examined and sorted the word counts,
단어수 벡터를 조사하고 정렬했듯이
we're not gonna examine sorting the TF ideas.
TF-IDF를 조사하고 정렬할 겁니다
I'm gonna reread the variable for Obama,
최종 버전에서 새로운 열 두 개를 추가했으니
because we now added these two new columns in the latest version of that.
오바마 변수를 다시 읽어들입니다
So I'm gonna take people, and I'm gonna select out of the people, the one whose
인물 중에서 이름이 바락 오바마인
name is equal to Barack Obama.
사람을 찾습니다
Okay, I've done it, I've created this Obama, and now, just like we did with word
오바마를 생성했고 단어수 때와 같이
counts, I will create an obama_tfidf_table so that we can sort it too.
obama_tfidf_table를 만들어서 정렬합니다
It's a dictionary.
사전 형식입니다
We're just gonna sort to the exactly the same way as we did before.
전과 같은 방식으로 정렬합니다
We will stack it and then sort it.
쌓고 나서 정렬합니다
And we're gonna do this.
이제 해보죠
Actually, instead of create a table, I'm just gonna do it in one line.
표를 만들지 않고 한 줄로 처리합니다
Oops, I'm gonna do just in one line here.
아 한 줄로 해볼게요
So I'm gonna write out what we did earlier, so
아까 했던 것처럼
I'm gonna just take the obama variable and
오바마 변수에서
when I select only the tfidf column so it looks a little prettier.
TF-IDF 열만 골라내면 깔끔하게 나옵니다
Then I'm gonna call the stack method, which takes a dictionary and
스택 메소드를 호출하면 사전을 입력 받아
just stacks it into two columns.
두 열로 쌓습니다
So I'm gonna stack tfidf.
TF-IDF를 쌓게 되죠
And I'm going to output new column names and
새 열 이름을 출력하는데
those names are going to be the word and
이름은 단어와 TF-IDF가 됩니다
the tfidf, and let me show you something.
신기한 걸 하나 보여드리죠
Ooops, I, Forgot to close, click it here.
아 괄호를 닫지 않았네요
And let me show you a little neat trick that you can use with Python in
파이썬에서 다양한 방법으로 쓸 수 있는
various ways.
요령 하나를 보여드리죠
I'm just gonna chain the source comment at the end of this.
이 뒤로 sort 함수를 체이닝합니다
So I'm just gonna type .sort.
.sort를 입력합니다
And I'm gonna sort this output on the tfidf column.
TF-IDF 열의 출력을 정렬합니다
And I'm gonna say ascending=false.
오름차순을 거짓으로 설정합니다
So what I did in multiple lines before, now I'm doing it in just one line.
이전엔 몇 줄에 걸쳐 써야 했던 걸 이제는 한 줄로 됩니다
I'm taking the obama column tfidf.
오바마의 TF-IDF 열에서
I'm gonna stack it into a word column, tfidf column, and
단어 열, TF-IDF 열을 쌓아서
now I'm gonna sort it in descending order.
내림차순으로 정렬합니다
So from highest to lowest.
높은 데서 낮은 순으로요
And if you remember, just before we run this.
이건 돌리기 전에 어땠는지 회상해보죠
When we did it for just word count you look like this.
단어수만 셌을 땐 이랬습니다
There was the most popular word, then in, then and, then of,
가장 많이 나오는 단어는 the, in, and, of
then to, his, then Obama, act, a, and he.
his, Obama, act, a, he 순이었죠
So those words are mostly uninformative except for the word Obama.
오바마 빼고는 별로 가치가 없는 정보입니다
So let's execute it for TF-IDF.
TF-IDF를 실행해보죠
And what we see here, voila, the most informative word is Obama
여기서 가장 정보가치가 높은 단어는 오바마인데
which makes a lot of sense because the article is about him.
문서가 그의 관한 것임을 상기해보면 당연한 결과죠
But then you have art, Iraq, control, law, ordered,
그다음 art, Iraq, control, law, ordered,
military, involvement, response, democratic, as in Democratic Party.
military, involvement, response, democratic, 민주당의 민주 순입니다
So you see, lots of action going on here around
오바마에 관한 주요 단어들이
words that are important, with respect to Obama.
여럿 등장함을 알 수 있죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]